[waves crashing]
♪ [music] ♪
- The Exuma Cays Land and Sea Park
in the Bahamas
is one of the oldest
marine protected areas in the world.
A man-made sanctuary in the sea.
The water is teemed with life
from the smallest to the largest
creature in the food chain
because they are protected from
the most efficient predator
our oceans have ever known.
♪ [music] ♪
- Now, where do you...?
- Well, I reckon if you
fish off that point...
- Yes.
- I'll cast the fly straight out.
Oh, what's that?
- Probably a bat.
- Look there.
Hey, hey.
Look!
Rupert, there's fish here.
- I came into this because
in a very small and very limited way,
I was a hunter of fish.
My first salmon,
my first salmon,
also the largest I ever caught--
here we come--
on a Welsh river, 23 lbs.
I was chaffed a bit to catch that.
Wooh, huge fin.
I have never been more proud of myself.
It was the last that anybody caught
on that beach for years and years.
I don't think anybody has caught
one as big as that, since.
And I was triumphant
but I also have felt guilty
about that fish ever since
because it was one
of the last of the spring run
that now no longer happens.
Now why were few of them coming back?
Well, I don't know
but I thought I better find out
and that's really what
set me off on this journey
to find out what was happening
to fish in the sea.
[motor running]
[office hustle and bustle]
[phone ringing]
-It's Clover, Charles Clover.
I've got some queries.
- Sir?
- What is the tuna that you serve?
Which ocean is it from
and how is it caught?
As a journalist,
what changed my view of the sea
was when I walked into the wrong
press conference in the Hay in 1990.
And this was the first
presentation I'd ever seen
about the effect of trawling
upon the seabed
and upon these creatures
that lived on it.
And what they said was
that trawling with the beam trawler
was like plowing a field
seven times a year.
And I'm a farmer's son,
and I thought to myself,
how many crops would grow if
you plow that field seven times a year?
And I thought not very much at all.
And that changed my whole view
of what was going on in the sea.
♪ [music] ♪
Our view of the sea has always been that
it is huge, beautiful, and inexhaustible.
♪ [music] ♪
The oceans are the common heritage
of all mankind
and for billions of years
they have been full of life.
These huge resources, these--
that we once believed to be renewable,
that our whole human history
has led us up to now to believe
that our renewable
are not renewable anymore
because of what we're doing to them.
And so, our entire
philosophical approach has to change.
It's not gonna be the same
in the future as it was in the past.
That's where we are now.
♪ [music] ♪
We never used to think about
where our fish came from,
but in fact they're wild animals.
And we found that out to our cost
for the first time in NewFoundland.
For centuries the waters
of Northern Canada
teemed with unbelievable amounts
of codfish.
Legend had it that you could
walk across their backs on the water.
The cod was so plentiful,
the communities thrived on fishing.
As the years went on, technology improved.
The boats got bigger
and catches increased.
The bounty seemed endless.
Then in 1992, the unthinkable happened.
[waves crashing]
[rumpus]
- In Saint John's tonight,
angry fishermen vented their rage.
They charged the room where
John Crosbie was holding
a news conference
but security would not let them in.
- What had once been the most abundant
Cod population in the world
had been fished out of existence.
- I've decided that effective
at midnight tonight,
there will be a moratorium
on harvesting the Northern Cod
until the spring of 1994.
- Either we cooperate in addressing it
or there's gonna be no fish for anybody.
No fish for the Europeans,
no fish for the Canadians,
and an ecological catastrophe
on our hands.
- With or without you.
With or without you and not only me,
every fishermen on his own
weren't going fishing.
- Overnight,
40,000 people lost their jobs.
- The cod is gone.
And I think within the context of cod,
particularly in the Canadian perspective,
is that this is a species that has been
fished for centuries and centuries.
Cod was the reason that people migrated
from the U.K., from Europe,
Northern France, in particular,
to Canada.
It was because of cod.
- The fishing ban brought
the people to the streets.
They hope that one day
the cod would return.
- The significance didn't drop.
It didn't dawn on anybody
until much later.
- Today, there are so few left
that they're--
they got a dangered status in Canada
and the Cod populations
have not rebounded
despite a moratorium
on cod fishing since 1992.
- In 2007, this research vessel
set two lines,
each with 1500 hooks
to find out
how many cod were left
in the waters off Eastern Canada.
On the first line,
they caught one small codfish.
On the second, a small basket full.
The cod stocks had been depleted
to such a low level that
they were unable to recover.
For Newfoundland, for a community
for which the whole reason
for it's existence was cod,
there's this historical
ingrained element.
It's part of society, permeates society
and the loss of the fish was basically--
it came to sort of a loss of soul
and it still remains that 15 years later.
- After the collapse of the cod,
a new breed of fishery scientists
started to investigate
what had been happening
to all the fish in every ocean
of the world.
Local catches of fish had been
declining almost everywhere.
But what puzzled the scientists in 2001,
was that the total world catch
kept going up and up.
It didn't make sense.
- The concerns that people had expressed
that local stocks
were going down everywhere
but that global statistics
were showing an increase,
that this was a discrepancy.
- Daniel Pauly,
a leading expert in global fishing,
was asked by the United Nations
Food and Agricultural Organization,
to investigate this mystery.
- Daniel Pauly had the brilliance
to start examining why
in the face of the evidence
that you saw in front of you, locally,
and in the face of evidence
like Newfoundland
that the figures kept going up.
- It was when Pauly and his colleagues
looked at the reported catches from China
that they found their answer.
- For every part of the world,
the reporting was right
except for Chinese waters.
- When Daniel Pauly
came to this department
and he said, "I think they're wrong."
And I said,
"What do you mean they're wrong?"
He said, "Well, it can't be that China
is catching that much."
- And they found that--
actually, when you look at the
biological productivity of the sea,
and what we know
about everywhere else,
the Chinese figures could not be right.
They were just made up.
They were made up by communist officials
who only got performant
if the graphs went up.
Graphs kept going up because
they kept making up the figures
and it was a huge seismic moment.
- We concluded that
they were so biased
upward so much
that if you corrected
for this effect,
the world catch would not be
increasing but decreasing.
- For the first time in human history,
the future of the food
the world gets from the sea was in doubt.
- It sends a shiver down my spine
because that was the one thing
that a lot of people were holding on to.
Well, things maybe bad,
but, at least
they're catching lots
and they're catching
more every year or so.
You know, it can't be that bad.
- From about 1988,
we now realize that
it was on the way down.
We only figured that out in 2002.
- All of these things were
like warning signals
and they were telling a story in aspects.
- This is a story that was going on
at the same time as
human influences elsewhere.
But it's been told late.
It's been told,
we haven't had so much time
to do something about it.
Now, it's on us and now in the next
maybe 40, 50 years, it's crisis,
it's crash,
it's let's do something about it time.
And that is why, this is, arguably,
one of the biggest problems in the world.
♪ [music] ♪
Man has been hunting fish in the sea
since he discovered they were there.
[waves splashing]
[motor running]
♪ [music] ♪
For the last 3,000 years,
these men and their forefathers
have expected
giant Bluefin tuna to migrate
from the Atlantic ocean
to the Mediterranean sea.
And every spring,
the fishermen set their trap,
an ancient method of fishing
known as the almadraba.
[harvesting]
♪ [music] ♪
The almadraba fishermen once
used to catch thousands of Bluefin.
But over the last ten years,
their catches have declined by 80%.
- If there are Tuna then there is joy.
Everyone shouts,
"Long live the Virgin of Carmen!"
It's euphoria.
Compared to how it was
when I arrived 22 years ago,
it really isn't the same.
This place had a lot of life.
Our wives and children were here.
Now my kids no longer come because
the situation isn't very good.
And my wife stays with the kids.
It's sad that I'm 45 years old
and talking of this,
because I wanted it to be so much better.
[water flowing]
- On the other side of the world,
in Canada,
scientist, Boris Worm,
had been trying to work out
how many tuna and other large fish
were left in the sea.
- Somebody said, counting fish
is just as easy as counting trees,
it's just that they are invisible,
and they move.
So, it's an almost impossible thing to do,
especially, when you want to assess
how the global ocean has changed,
the whole thing.
We asked that very simple question,
where are we now relative
to the baseline
that we set around 1950,
because large scale industrial fishing
started around 1950.
So, here in 1952, when the series starts,
we see that around Japan,
there's already blue colors dominating,
meaning that the capture rates were low
around one fish per hundred folks.
In areas, that were newly exploited,
we see capture rates
about 10 times higher.
Ten or more fish per a hundred hooks.
- Worm used Japanese fishing fleet data
that had recorded how many fish were
caught on every hundred hooks they set.
- This is the first time,
industrial long line fishing
is let out into the open ocean
and just worked through
the whole ecosystem.
♪ [music] ♪
And you see that the fishery has reached
a truly global coverage
and a lot of the ocean
is in the blue colors now.
Meaning, that the abundance
of these large fish, globally,
has probably declined by about 90%.
This has been widely criticized
and there'd been many papers written
to undermine and attack these findings.
- Totally wrong.
That's there is just no question,
that's totally wrong.
- Some fishery scientists felt that
Worm's findings
didn't reflect their local situation.
Some thought that
even attempting to count
how many large fish
were left in all the oceans,
was an impossible task.
- I think that in their haste
to get the big picture,
they-- they don't look
carefully enough at local places.
- They actually disagree with one thing,
a certain tuna, yellow fin,
and escape jack in the Pacific.
And there are--
they say it's only 70%, not 90%.
- Whether it's 90 or 95 or 80 or 70,
is rather irrelevant.
We all know they've declined,
dramatically.
So, focusing on the particulars,
in that sense, is not helpful.
- The overall trends in Worm's findings
were reflected in official data.
Species after species had collapsed.
- Everybody recognizes that there's
major problems in the world's fisheries.
And, at one level, it's a question of how,
you know, of how bad is it?
[waves splashing]
- Today, in every ocean of the world,
high-tech industrial vessels are
hunting down every known
edible species of fish.
- The basic problem in most fisheries
that are in trouble is too many boats.
- Too much capacity chasing too few fish.
- Global fishing capacity could catch
the world catch four times over.
The worlds long lining industry
set 1.4 billion hooks every year.
These are estimated to be set on
more than 550 times.
A mouth of the
largest trawling net in the world
is big enough
to accommodate thirteen 747s.
- We are fighting a war
against this, right?
And we are throwing up our industry,
and we are winning.
And that's how we perceive
our interaction with them.
It's a fight.
- The thing is we're too good right now.
Technologically, not a single
hunted animal on this earth has a chance.
- These vessels are equipped with
so much electronic equipment that
the fish have actually
no chance of escaping.
These people knows exactly where he is
in relationship to a rock
where fish could hide,
in relationship to a wreck,
where a fish would be attracted to.
- It doesn't take very long for us to have
very serious consequences
in what we're doing.
We're not willing--
We keep passing the buck.
We're not willing to hold back.
- The might of the fishing armory has
grown exponentially in the last 50 years.
The amount of fishing power
that we have at our command today
far outweighs
our ability to control ourselves.
Fishing has transformed
the entire ecosystems.
In fact, I would say
one of the largest scale transformation
of the planetary environment
has been the impact of bottom trawlers,
that's sort of dragged across the seabed
and as they are pulled,
they cut down the animals
that live on the surface,
things like corals,
and seafans, and sponges.
But, the signs of destruction
brought up on that by the trawl
would make an angel weep.
- If the fishing effort
continued to increase,
continued to be directed
at the dwindling results,
you would of course catch most of it.
- The Bluefin is one of the
most iconic fish in the sea.
It's beautiful hydro-dynamic shape
and specially heated blood,
allow it to accelerate faster
than a super car.
Pound for pound, it's delicious flesh
is the most expensive
and sought after on the planet.
The Bluefin once sustained
roman legions in battle.
Now, it feeds fashion conscious dinners
in sushi restaurants around the world.
- Bluefin is the front liner.
Bluefin is the most immediate crisis
that we know about.
- For many years,
scientists have been predicting
that the king of the tuna
will be hunted to extinction.
But now, it is actually happening.
Roberto Mielgo is
a Bluefin Tuna fisherman
who has turned whistle blower
on an industry
he believes is out of control.
A lone presence in the ports of Europe,
Mielgo is hunting for information
to bring the slaughter to a halt.
- It's Bluefin.
I can--
I can actually tell from here,
it's Bluefin.
I started in this business
as a tuna farm diver,
that was many years ago.
Those days were the good old days,
where the stock was healthy, I would say.
But, then Bluefin tuna
became big business.
I mean, really big business.
In 2002, I was in Tunisia,
I think it was,
and that's when I first sensed that
something terribly wrong was happening.
The conflict was that I saw that
it's something
that I could not control.
And as from there, I took the
decision to try and do the right thing.
That is a Bluefin unloading.
Let's say--
let's say there's only two containers
and they jam pack
those two reefer containers,
40 feet reefer containers
with 28-tons each.
That is 56 tons of fish,
which is more than what Taiwan
would normally declare as catches
at the end of the fishing season.
So, there you go. I mean...
- One boat?
- Just one boat.
What's at stake here is of--
an infamous minority
of people making millions
and millions and millions
by decimating a specie.
Is that right?
Is that moral?
- In Luxembourg,
European Union ministers meet
to decide the faith of the fish
and an industry which depends on it.
Fishing is supposed to be controlled
through internationally agreed quotas,
the amount fishermen
are allowed to catch.
These are recommended by scientists.
- What will happen this afternoon
and, and what it will mean
for the Bluefin tuna?
- Well, what will happen is that
fisheries ministers of the Europe
will take a decision that goes against
the-- any rational scientific advise
for the conservation of Bluefin.
- Bluefin scientists are recommending
a catch of 15,000 tons
simply to avoid collapse.
In order to rebuild the fish population,
the catch needs to be less,
at 10,000 tons.
But, ministers vote
for a catch of 29,500 tons,
twice what it should be
to keep the population from crashing,
and three times what it should be
to let the fish recover.
- I just can't accept that.
This is a political poaching.
It's negotiating with biology
and you just can't do that
and expect to see the biology survive.
- This is a species which
is endangered as the white Rhinoceros
and yet it's being hunted
to extinction in the Mediterranean.
It's being exploited to more than
twice the level that it should be
and those countries that have over fished
are not being forced
to pay back whatever they fish.
So, not a day in which the European Union
has covered itself in glory.
- Bluefin tuna is not the only fish
whose stocks have declined dramatically.
And most of the others have declined
while under the supervision
of the scientists and politicians
in the riches nations of the world.
- If fisheries managers were engineers
they would have been fired long ago,
because, you know,
we'd be having collapsing buildings
and bridges all over the place
because their calculations are so far out.
And so, it's not a question of,
if fish stocks will collapse
when you make decisions like that,
it's a question simply of the when.
Collapse is inevitable.
- This is the center
of the Bluefin tuna universe.
Malta is that.
- Roberto Mielgo has come to Malta
to investigate whether the tuna industry
is catching more than the quota allows.
- Hello, Charles. How are you doing?
- How are you getting on?
- Oh well, busy.
- Have you found a lot?
- Quite a lot.
- Despite the scientists recommending
an annual catch of 15,000 tons
and the politicians setting 30,000 tons,
official figures show that
the Mediterranean Bluefin tuna industry
simply ignores the regulations
and catches 61,000 tons,
a third of the entire
Bluefin tuna population.
Mielgo discovers that
some fishermen will stop at nothing
to get hold of this
sought after commodity.
- I flew to Lampedusa the other day
and just by chance
I came across some interesting documents.
- Is there anything to--
to link them to a fishing activity?
- So, they can catch
as many fish as possible,
the fleets use planes
to spot the tuna shoals,
an activity that has been outlawed
during this part of the season
for the last 10 years.
[foreign language]
- Mostly, these planes where
operated by Italian fishing fleets,
fishing South of Lampedusa,
East of Tunisia,
and outside Libyan waters.
This is a disgrace.
The Italian government
isn't doing a thing.
Nobody is enforcing the rule of law.
This is a disgrace for the European Union.
[water splashing]
- The breaking of the rules by fishermen
is one of the biggest problems
facing the world's oceans.
Illegal, unregulated,
and unreported fishing
is worth up to $25 billion a year.
- Fishermen cheat because they can.
Fishermen cheat
because they don't get caught.
But, that's true of all the systems.
- A study for the house of Lords
in the United Kingdom,
reported that 50% of the cod caught
in the North Sea was illegal.
- Every other fish on your plate
was stolen-- stolen from you.
[bell tolls]
- Mielgo has come to Tokyo,
the center of the world tuna trade
where last ditch attempts are being made
to save the majestic Bluefin.
[foreign language]
- The biggest company in the tuna business
is the multi-national Mitsubishi,
makers of cars and electrical products.
They don't actually catch the fish,
they just buy it.
- I would think that
Mitsubishi corporation, itself,
would be in control of something
like 60% of all of the entire
Bluefin tuna production,
Northern Bluefin tuna production
in the Atlantic and the Mediterranean.
- Mielgo is here to attend a meeting
of the International Committee for the
Conservation of the Atlantic Tuna, ICCAT,
which has been called in a desperate
attempt to persuade the industry
to stick to internationally
agreed quotas.
- Roberto speaking here in Tokyo.
- How are you getting on?
- Well, it's been a humbling experience,
Charles.
-Mielgo had discovered that Mitsubishi
were sending out new,
larger boats to bring back Bluefin.
- They have pumped up their
freezing and transportation capacity.
- Mitsubishi claimed to control less
than 40% of the Bluefin import market
and say the new boats
where sent to replace old vessels.
But, Mielgo believes that
Mitsubishi and other traders
are building up frozen reserves
which will be worth much more
if fish stocks are depleted.
- If there's no more Bluefin tuna caught,
but you're sitting on 60,
70,000 tons of it, frozen,
you name the price.
- Mitsubishi say they try to provide
the Japanese market with stable supplies
at reasonable prices
while supporting policies
to ensure long term
sustainability of the stock.
But, Mielgo fears that the result will
still be the extinction of the species.
- The immediate conclusion
one has to come up to
is that these guys want to fish
until the very last Bluefin tuna.
And once they have caught
the very last Bluefin tuna,
they will go on to Bigeye tuna.
And once they have over fished
Bluefin, er-- Bigeye tuna,
they will go for another tuna specie.
- Mitsubishi insists
they wanna preserve the tuna
for future generations and
they support cuts in the Bluefin quota.
The faith of Bluefin shows
what multi-national corporations,
international fisheries policy and
consumer demand can do to a wild species.
But the race to catch the last fish,
whatever it's price,
is happening all over the world.
♪ [music] ♪
- Hundreds of millions
of people in the world
depend on fish to keep them alive.
For 1.2 billion people,
it is a key part of their diet.
In West Africa, which used to have
one of the richest seas on the planet,
the stocks of fish have declined
massively in the last 50 years.
Rashid Sumaila is an expert
on West African fisheries
who has come to Senegal to find out
what effect this has had on local people.
- Fish is crucial in West Africa.
I mean the coastal people depend on fish
and even the interior people come down
when the funds disappoint them,
when there's drought,
there's extra and so on.
So, it is very important
to keep this going
for the sake of the people
because if the fish goes down,
the coast of West Africa
will be littered with problems.
We cannot afford to let this go.
- Adoma Mbergaul is an artisanal fisherman
who lives in Dakar,
the capital of Senegal.
Fishing is his livelihood.
[foreign language]
- Fishing is our culture. We are 'Lebou.'
- We belong to this
particular ethnic group
which is passed on from
the tradition of our grandparents.
When I was a young boy
what I witnessed with my own eyes
was a sea full of fish.
There used to be fish in abundance.
And our Grandfathers encouraged us
to follow in their footsteps.
But the sea betrayed us.
- Today, Adoma earns
$6.00 from his fishing.
His fuel cost him $4.00,
what is left has to feed his family.
[foreign language]
- Meanwhile on the same shoreline,
money is being made.
The government
of many developing countries
trade fishing rights for quick cash
from developed nations.
Tax payers from the Western world
pay for the largest fishing boats
on the planet,
super trawlers,
to fish the distant water.
The locals in their pirogues
don't stand a chance.
- That's no good for the fishermen,
that's no good for our sea.
That's good just for European fishermen
and government of Senegal
because they have lot of money.
- Haidar has dived the waters of Senegal
for the last 35 years
and has witnessed huge changes
to the health of the local ocean.
He is campaigning against
foreign boats fishing in his waters.
- When I see this,
I want to fight with this guy.
I want to fight with this artisanal boat.
I want to fight with the government
who take just the money
and don't know what they do.
I want to fight with the world because
the world's going to be-- to be dead.
It's not flexible.
- Fishing is one of the most wasteful
practices on earth.
Every year, more than 7 million tons,
a tenth of the worlds catch
goes back over the side, dead.
This includes hundreds of thousands of
turtles, sea birds,
sharks, whales, and dolphins.
- See, how he do to destroy the ocean?
He take just what he want.
He take just what he need to sell, now.
But, the fish, he don't need to sell that.
He put them out and he'd kill them.
Look all around you.
- As the fish had been taken
by foreign fleets,
fishermen like Adoma have been left
with an impossible decision,
should he leave his family
and risk the dangerous journey to Europe?
- For me the truth is,
that things are very, very tough.
When I think about leaving for Europe,
I feel something in my body.
I know it is safe and it is not safe.
Because I know the dangers of the sea.
But I have no choice.
Look at my daughter,
If my children grow up here today,
where there is no future,
how will they consider me as their father?
♪ [music] ♪
- The fish goes,
the people are made poorer
and what happens, they try to immigrate.
The Europeans like our fish
but they don't like the people.
The fish has visa to come in
but the people are turned back.
♪ [music] ♪
- I think that if man
is not going to change
and the sea is going to be dead
because man is crazy.
We are crazy.
Our world is crazy world.
[city hustle and bustle]
- In the restaurants of Asia,
diners are buying live fish
in greater quantities than ever before.
These are being taken from
the most beautiful parts of the planet,
the Coral Triangle.
The Coral Triangle is an area of ocean
half the size of the United States,
in the seas of Southern Asia.
Coral Reefs were targeted as
a food supply when local waters run out.
The most desirable fish
are the reefs large, colorful predators.
Our insatiable appetite
for such delicacies
threatens to tip the fragile balance
of nature into chaos.
- We don't know what the implications are
of losing some of these very--
one particular component of the ecosystem.
We just know that in every ecosystems
there have been problems.
And that when we mess around
with nature,
there's usually problems.
- In the East Coast of America,
there is a terrifying clue
of what can happen
when you disturb
the ocean's natural equilibrium.
- We've got a big surprise for you.
We've got Chesapeake ray.
[harvesting ruckus]
- Most people don't use it as a food
'cause it's a little difficult to get to.
- In Chesapeake Bay,
there have been increasing reports
of a plague of biblical proportions.
A little know inhabitant of the bay
the cownose ray has exploded in numbers.
Local scientist, Pete Peterson,
was investigating the increase
in the cownose ray population
when he noticed
that the graph of their growth
was the exact opposite of the graph
of the decline in their main predator,
the shark.
- Even a number
of quality scientists
will tell you that--
that statistics are in some ways
icing on the cake
when you do your science.
But, to tell you the truth,
as you look at a plot
of how the numbers of sharks
along these coasts have changed,
how the numbers of rays, skates,
and smaller sharks
have changed at the same time,
you don't need a statistic at all.
It jumps right off the page at you.
- When large predators are taken out,
when they're depleted
in abundance as much as they are,
we have large ecosystem effects that
can cause all sorts of domino effects
through out the ecosystem.
A lot of them surprising,
unforeseen effects.
-There's evidence of this knock-on effect
happening all over the world.
In NewFoundland,
lobster numbers are exploding.
- The loss of cod
and other bottom dwelling fish,
as what we have seen is an increase
in the abundance of other things.
So, in this part of the Atlantic
there's always been
a fair number of lobster
but there is now, evidently,
quite a bit more.
So, it seems
fairly reasonable to conclude
that the decline of cod
and other predatory fishes
has, basically, paved the way
for an increase in
the abundance of those things
that cod used to eat.
- Fishermen have eagerly
fed off the bonanza.
There is big money
to be made in lobster.
But, how long will it last?
- This is the situation
that happens everywhere
we have removed the fish, the last fish.
In many places,
what has exploded is the shrimp.
Shrimp have exploded.
This good shrimp, good money.
But if you'll overfish them, what then?
- The end point is when the prawns
and the scallops too have gone.
We really will be down to a highly
simplified ecosystem of mud and worms.
- Jellyfish infestations are increasing.
Beaches are becoming no-go zones.
Our oceans once full of large fish
are now filling up with algae,
plankton, and worms.
- Plankton sticks pressed
into fish shaped pieces,
perhaps, Jellyfish burgers?
The options are endless.
♪ [music] ♪
- The losing species,
what does that mean for us?
What does that mean for society?
What does it mean for the
predictability of the global oceans,
which is 70% of the planet?
And the answer is,
with every species that disappears,
some of those services are eroding.
There is less food.
There is declining water quality.
And there is declining stability
of the system.
What alarmed me the most was that
the ability of the system
to absorb shocks and disasters,
to deal with climate change,
to deal with overfishing was diminishing.
It could be a road of no return.
- According to data collected
by the United Nations,
the number of fish species
whose populations have crashed
is growing year by year.
Worm and the other scientists
have projected that
if the current trends continue,
the stocks of fish which we now eat
will have collapsed
by the middle of the century.
- What we noticed was the curves,
they were separating the
high and low diversity curves,
but they are both dropping.
- All the fish and the invertebrates
that we eat,
that supply us with seafood,
we found that by 2003,
about one-third of them
were in what we call collapsed state.
Over the last 50 years,
there was a very, very clear trend
of year after year after year,
more of these species
were in that collapsed category.
- They started very high,
they kept dropping
and dropping and dropping and dropping.
And if you take those curves,
and say, "Well, they're dropping."
"When are they gonna hit zero?"
When are they gonna
drop down to the point
where the fisheries that we're used to
are no longer gonna be possible.
And those curves drop down
and they hit zero about 2048.
- This is not some horror scenario.
It's a real possibility.
And it's not rocket science
because if we're depleting
one species after another,
it's a finite resource, there will be a
point in the future where we will run out
if we don't change
the way we treat this global resource.
- Worm and the others were criticized by
their opponents for naming a precise date.
But, this was not the point
they were making.
- Whoever makes
an interpolation makes it
always assuming that
things remain the same.
And I would say that
assuming that things remain the same,
this prediction that
we will have no fish in 50 years or so,
are essentially correct.
- When the human population
comes under real pressure on land,
when we begin to have real problems
from global warming,
when we start running out of
enough food to feed ourselves,
we have just squandered
one of the greatest resources
that we've ever had on the planet,
wild fish.
That's what it means.
♪ [music] ♪
- For generations,
men have hunted the world's oceans.
For generations, we've eaten fish.
What can our generation do
to stop us reaching the end of the line?
♪ [music] ♪
- Fish, I love fish, eating fish not meat.
I can eat fish four times a day.
My son doesn't like it.
If I cook fish, he said,
"No more meal. I want chicken."
And I said, "Fish is good for the body."
He said, "No."
Well, I love fish other than two piece.
- Well, I love to eat fish.
So, fish are--
Fish are food to me.
♪ [music] ♪
- Lots of the time people say,
where are all the fish?
Ninety percent of the fish is gone.
Where are they? We have eaten them.
That's what we have, we have eaten them.
♪ [music] ♪
- When we look at
a piece of fish on our plate,
what do we know about that fish?
We know it's good for us.
We know it's probably got
some omega-3 fatty acids
which are good
for all our organ functions.
But, what else do we know about it?
What do we know about it?
Do we know what species it is?
Do we know whether
it was caught legally or illegally
or in the waters of some distant country
where the inhabitants would actually
prefer to have caught it themselves?
- Hello, Ingrid.
It's Charles Clover
from the Daily Telegraph.
I noticed that Marlin was on the menu.
This is a kind of an unusual
fish to find on the menu
and I wondered which species
of Marlin this was,
'cause I thought there wasn't
an awful lot of Marlin left?
Both these fish, the Bluefin tuna
and the-- Sea Bass
are listed as endangered species.
I wanted to talk to someone
who would know about
the sourcing policy for fish
at Nobu restaurants,
can we send them an e-mail?
No, we can't.
- British journalist, Charles Clover
has been trying to find out what is sold
in some of the most exclusive
restaurants of the world.
After five years of no comment,
eventually Nobu agreed to talk.
- Hello.
- Hello, Mr. Clover. How are you?
- Hello, Mr. Notar. How are you?
- I feel like I know you.
[laughing]
- You've got a fish that is actively
been described as endangered since 1996
and you're serving it in your restaurants.
- Not only are we going to describe
what it is on the menu,
I'm gonna put an asterisk next to it
and at the bottom of the menu
I'm going to say,
"You know, it is an endangered--
an environmentally endangered species."
Just so people know.
That's the first immediate step
that we can do.
Then we also...
- It's a sort of, how it'll sell?
You have some endangered species,
are people gonna buy that, do you think?
- Well, I mean you know,
you're boxing me into a corner.
At one point people are saying,
"You're not being informative."
At some point people have
to make decisions on their own.
If you look at a pack of cigarettes,
it has a warning sign saying,
"This will kill you."
- The question people will want to know is
why you just don't take it off
the menu now?
If you got orangutans
and, you know, cheetahs,
and lions and tigers and things,
on that menu,
I mean, people would, you know,
they're walking away.
There'd be huge scandals.
There'd be tabloid stories about it.
People would be execrated.
People that would be--
on people's doorsteps
and in envelopes
being shoved through them.
People would, you know,
burn each other's houses down
and scratching their cars.
And yet, we're doing it to things in
the sea and we're doing the same thing.
- This fish is modern, cool, refreshing,
looks really, really like flashy,
but it's that-- that simple.
So, I've got some beautiful Bluefin tuna.
- Now, that these kind of popular
television programs with celebrity chefs
have made fish fashionable,
is it too late to save
the world's oceans?
- People ask me all the time,
are you despairing or are you hopeful?
And I'm saying, absolutely hopeful.
And they ask, what makes you think that?
And I say, well two things.
One is, now, we have
a much better understanding
than even five years ago, what's going on.
And there's a track record
of when we understood changes
and they became public knowledge.
They entered people's consciousness,
like with pollution,
like with ozone depletion,
like with climate change, more recently.
Things started to happen
and people made changes.
- I think that there's a message of hope
because there's still time
for us to turn the course of history.
And, although,
the players have taken poison,
there's still time to save them.
[crowd talking]
♪ [music] ♪
- Alaska in on the front line in
the battle to conserve fish.
- According to the U.N.,
according to the only laws that we have,
all the sea-- the sea belongs to us,
the citizens.
Known to the fishermen,
known to the aggregates industry,
know to the oil and gas industries,
it's ours.
So, why don't we claim it back.
♪ [music] ♪
- Alaska has a 200 mile fishing limit
which is strictly enforced.
- Portlock bank,
coordinates are gonna be 56.
It appears that they've been fishing
in one area and they're claiming another.
- One of the lessons in Alaska is first
you have to not allow new boats to enter
and you have to find mechanisms
to get some boats
to leave to match your fleet size
to the capacity of the resource.
- Alaska's fishing policy is not perfect,
but the number of fishing boats here
is carefully controlled.
And managers can monitor how much
is being caught and react accordingly.
Fishing policy here
is determined by the science.
Catch limits
are set well below the level
that fish populations can withstand.
- One of the differences between
Alaska and, let's say, the North Sea or--
is the that average
exploitation rate on stocks
in Alaska is on the order of 10% a year,
in the North Sea, it's 50%.
- One way in which Alaska
controls the catch is by giving
the fisherman a limited amount
of time to fulfill their quota.
- Flare! Flare! Flare!
[motor running]
♪ [music] ♪
- If you look at it
from just a personal perspective,
sometimes yet
there's a personal sacrifice.
But, if you look at it
from the big picture,
they got to take a cut in the harvest
but they take that knowing that
it gives you an opportunity to maybe have
a better season two, three, four,
or five years from now.
We just don't wanna catch that fish
this year or next year,
we wanna catch it
10, 15, 20 years from now.
- As consumers, we have the power
to bring about a positive change at sea
by demanding to know
where our fish comes from,
how it was caught,
and whether it is endangered.
- There's a fishing industry out there,
some of which,
is trying incredibly hard to get it right.
And they are not being supported
as much as they should be
because people are not recognizing
the difference between what they're doing
or the guys who are just
rampantly raping the seas are doing.
I think we have to support
that part of the fishing industry.
- For consumers,
there are guides to identifying
which fish is better to eat.
Then there are labels
which certify its sustainability.
One is issued by
the Marine Stewardship Council, the MSC.
- What we do and the choices we make
in say supermarkets,
when we go to a restaurant
actually has a direct effect
on marine diversity.
- At the moment, only a small proportion
of the fish we buy
comes from a sustainable source.
But with pressure,
things are slowly changing.
Even the worlds largest retail,
Wal-Mart has plans to sell only
MSC fresh and frozen fish by 2011.
- We sell approximately
20 million pounds of fresh fish a year.
We had to do something that
would protect us as we grow
and as we need more and more
product into the future.
And that's where the
MSC really shown out to us
as a leading way that we can really
embrace and grow our business.
- Birds Eye, once the king
of the codfish finger,
now buys over two-thirds
of their fish from sustainable sources.
And fast food outlet, McDonalds,
say that over 90% of their fish
comes from a sustainable source.
- Knowledge is power and what knowledge
gives you is the opportunity to change
the way that you do things,
to change the way you behave.
- More and more fish
are now being farmed.
Many people see this as an answer
to the increasingly
desperate problem facing our oceans.
But, fish farming
is not all that it seems.
Fish farming
uses wild fish to feed farm fish
but it kills more than it produces.
All of these anchovies will be ground up
for fish meal to feed fish
and other animals around the world.
- Like, a hundred million tons
is getting fished
every year in the planet,
40% go and get ground into fish meal
to feed other fish and not to feed people,
so that some rich people
somewhere in the world
can eat salmon and can eat shrimp.
- The more fish farming we do in the West,
the less fish we have.
This is one of the paradoxes
that people have big--
have a problem understanding.
- Aquaculture for species that eat fish,
doesn't have that much room to grow
because there just aren't many fish
out there in the ocean
to feed them anymore.
- You, actually, convert fish
from one species into the other.
You don't make more fish, at least,
not when you have farm fish.
- On average, five kilos of anchovy
make only one kilo of salmon.
- We've reached the buffers.
We have reached the limits
on what the ocean
is capable of providing
to feed the fish farming industry.
So, how can it grow if it's already
reached the end of it's feeds stock?
- Patricia has started a campaign
to encourage people all over the world
to eat small fish like anchovy,
herring, and mackerel,
instead of the farm fish
that are fed on them.
- Why not eat the fish directly?
Why not eat the anchovies?
They're much better for you
than salmon, anyways.
It's this tiny little fish
that has all the energy
that you need to be healthy.
- If fish farming is not the answer,
despite attempts
to make it less wasteful,
and sustainable fisheries
aren't catching on fast enough,
what else can we do
to save the world's oceans?
- We need to turn back the clock
200 years to bring back life,
to restore it's previous
abundance and productivity
in some places around the world oceans.
I'm talking about creating
a network of areas
within which we can turn back the clock.
[waves crashing]
- It's a nice country.
no time more beautiful than this.
Might as well die and go to heaven.
- Marine reserves
are areas of the world's oceans
where commercial fishing
is completely banned.
The results can be staggering.
- Wherever people have established
an area that's off limits to fishing
and policed it well,
they've been resolute
in that pursuit of protection,
reserves have shown marvelous benefits.
I've studied marine reserves
in the Caribbean
and there the local community
set up four areas that were
off limits to fishing in 1995.
Overtime you could see
the reef re-populating and refilling
and life was becoming
more abundant on them.
And, we saw an increase of
three, four, five times
of the amount of fish
that were present initially
over a period of seven years
of protection after that.
- Hardy McKinney is a fisherman
in South Andros, in the Bahamas
campaigning for a reserve to be
setup in an area decimated by fishing.
- Half this area is set aside
as a protected area.
No one is permitted to go in to fish
and you allow the fish to do what they do.
It's just a natural thing.
You would have more fish.
So, you would go to a rock
were there is one group
and next year you may see, two.
And then the following year,
you may see four.
And so, you know, naturally it would work.
- Marine reserves
are absolutely necessary.
But, they are necessary
and we must have lots of money.
- The best available calculation on
how much it will cost
to have a global network
of marine protected areas that you cover
between 20% and 30% of the area
in the world oceans, is that it would--
it would take about
12 to 14 billion dollars a year
to manage a network of that scale.
Compared to fishery subsidies,
the amount is roughly equivalent.
The fishery subsidy is estimated to be
of the order of about
15 to 30 billion dollars a year.
And those subsidies
encourage over fishing.
What this 12 to 14 billion dollar cost
of managing protected areas would do
would be to contribute
to the solution to over fishing
and in the process would create
about a million jobs world wide.
-The world has signed up
to establishing a network of
marine protected areas by 2012.
Some nations have promised
to protect 20% or more
of their seas in the future.
But, we have to put pressure on
governments to ensure this happens.
- We have about 4,000 marine reserves
of different sizes in the world.
They cover one-- less than 1%
of the world ocean, 0.6%, point six.
Ninety nine point four percent
of the ocean is fishable.
- You are allowed to fish
in 99% of the ocean.
Now, that doesn't seem to me
to be a proper representation
of our interests as citizens.
- Marine reserves on their own
will not solve the problem
of the emptying seas.
Fishermen and migratory fish
will move to unprotected areas,
so these also have to be controlled.
Politicians have to act responsibly
when making decisions about the oceans.
Consumers need to change
their eating habits.
And the global fishing industry
has to abide by the rules
and reduce it's capacity.
- The problem is getting political will
to implement these things.
And people will always argue,
"Well, you can't do this because it would
affect too many people's livelihoods."
Well, in the end, those livelihoods are
disappearing year by year with inaction.
- I want them to manage
the sea full recovery.
I want them--
I want it to be full of fish.
I want it to be full of cod and skate
and haddock and halibut
and, you know, shellfish
and everything.
- The society want
to see that recovery take place
or is it's society happy
with massive depletions?
I don't think my six-year old daughter
is gonna be particularly happy
in 10 years time
when she reads about this stuff
and learns about it and says,
"Dad, all this happened
in your life times."
In your life time-- my lifetime.
Anyone who's 30, 40, 50, 60 years old,
this has happened on our watch
and we have a collective responsibility.
- The difference between this and other
environmental problems is it actually--
it is relatively simple to solve.
We can act now.
It's not rocket science.
We don't need more knowledge to do so.
So, let's do what we can, where we can.
You can do it here, you can do it now.
You just do it.
♪ [music] ♪